<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<wikipedia lang="en">
<article name="Sparrow">
<redirect name="Sparow"/>
<redirect name="Spadger"/>
<redirect name="Passeridæ"/>
<redirect name="Old World sparrow"/>
<redirect name="Old world sparrow"/>
<redirect name="Passeridae"/>
<redirect name="Old World Sparrow"/>
<redirect name="Sparrows"/>
<links_in name="224"/>
<textlink name="Passeridae" freq="7"/>
<category name="Passeridae *"/>
<category name="Articles containing video clips"/>
<category name="Birds by common name"/>
<links_out name="119"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ang" name="Spearwa"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ar" name="دوري (فصيلة)"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="arc" name="ܨܦܪܐ (ܛܝܪܐ)"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="arz" name="عصفور"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="azb" name="سئرچه"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="be" name="Вераб’іныя"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="be-x-old" name="Вераб’іныя"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="bg" name="Врабчови"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="bn" name="চড়ুই"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="bo" name="ཁང་བྱིའུ།"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="br" name="Passeridae"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="bs" name="Vrabac"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="bxr" name="Борбилоогойхин"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ca" name="Passèrid"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ceb" name="Passeridae"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="chr" name="ᏥᏍᏆᏯ"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ckb" name="چۆلەکە"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="crh" name="Torğay"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="cs" name="Vrabcovití"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="cv" name="Çерçи йышшисем"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="da" name="Spurve"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="de" name="Sperlinge"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="el" name="Σπουργίτι"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="eo" name="Paseredoj"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="es" name="Passeridae"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="et" name="Varblaslased"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="eu" name="Txolarre"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="fa" name="گنجشک"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="fi" name="Varpuset"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="fo" name="Spurvur"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="fr" name="Passeridae"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="frr" name="Sparger"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ga" name="Gealbhan"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="gd" name="Glaisean"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="gl" name="Paséridos"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="gu" name="ચકલી"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="he" name="דרוריים"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="hr" name="Vrapci"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="hu" name="Verébfélék"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ia" name="Passeridae"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="id" name="Burung gereja"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="inh" name="Боккъонца дола хьазилгаш"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="it" name="Passeridae"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ja" name="スズメ科"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="jv" name="Sparrow"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="kn" name="ಗುಬ್ಬಚ್ಚಿ"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ko" name="참새과"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ks" name="ژٔر"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ksh" name="Mösch"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ku" name="Çivîk"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="kw" name="Golvan"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="lrc" name="میلیچأک"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="lt" name="Žvirbliniai"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="lv" name="Zvirbuļu dzimta"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="mdf" name="Кирьхкс"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ml" name="കുരുവി"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="mrj" name="Орави йишвлӓ"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="my" name="စာကလေး"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="myv" name="Озяз"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="mzn" name="میشکا"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ne" name="भँगेरा"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="nl" name="Mussen"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="nn" name="Sporvefamilien"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="no" name="Spurvefamilien"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="nv" name="Tsídiiłbáhí"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="or" name="ଚଟିଆ (ଚଢ଼େଇ)"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="os" name="Сырддонцъиу"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="pl" name="Wróble"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="pnb" name="چڑی"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="pt" name="Passeridae"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ro" name="Paseride"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="roa-rup" name="Vrapciu"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ru" name="Воробьиные"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="rue" name="Вороблёвы"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="sah" name="Барабыайдыҥылар кэргэннэрэ"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="sco" name="Sparrae"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="sh" name="Vrapci"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="simple" name="Sparrow"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="sr" name="Врапци (породица)"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="sv" name="Sparvfinkar"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ta" name="சிட்டு (பறவை)"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="te" name="పిచ్చుక"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="th" name="วงศ์นกกระจอก"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="tl" name="Pipit"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="tr" name="Serçe"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="uk" name="Горобцеві"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="ur" name="گھریلو چڑیا"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="vep" name="Pasklindud"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="vi" name="Họ Sẻ"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="war" name="Passeridae"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="xmf" name="ბაღჷრეშობურეფი"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="zh" name="雀科"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="zh-min-nan" name="Chhek-kho"/>
<crosslanguage_link language="zh-yue" name="麻雀科"/>
<content>
<p>Sparrows are a <link target="family (biology)">family</link> of small <link target="passerine">passerine</link> <link target="bird">bird</link>s. They are also known as true sparrows, or <link target="Old World">Old World</link> sparrows, names also used for a particular <link target="genus">genus</link> of the family, <link target="Passer">Passer</link>. They are distinct from both the <link target="American sparrow">American sparrow</link>s, in the family <link target="Passerellidae">Passerellidae</link>, and from a few other birds sharing their name, such as the <link target="Java sparrow">Java sparrow</link> of the family <link target="Estrildidae">Estrildidae</link>. Many species nest on buildings and the <link target="House sparrow">house</link> and <link target="Eurasian tree sparrow">Eurasian tree sparrow</link>s, in particular, inhabit cities in large numbers, so sparrows are among the most familiar of all wild birds. They are primarily <link target="seed">seed-eaters</link>, though they also consume small <link target="insect">insect</link>s. Some species scavenge for food around cities and, like <link target="gull">gull</link>s or <link target="rock dove">rock dove</link>s will happily eat virtually anything in small quantities.<h>Description</h></p>
<p>Generally, sparrows are small, plump, brown and grey birds with short tails and stubby, powerful <link target="beak">beak</link>s. The differences between sparrow species can be subtle. Members of this family range in size from the <link target="chestnut sparrow">chestnut sparrow</link> (Passer eminibey), at   and  , to the <link target="parrot-billed sparrow">parrot-billed sparrow</link> (Passer gongonensis), at   and  . Sparrows are physically similar to other seed-eating birds, such as <link target="finch">finch</link>es, but have a vestigial dorsal outer <link target="primary feather">primary feather</link> and an extra bone in the tongue. This bone, the preglossale, helps stiffen the tongue when holding seeds. Other adaptations towards eating seeds are specialised bills and elongated and specialised <link target="alimentary canal">alimentary canal</link>s.<h>Taxonomy and systematics</h></p>
<p>
The family Passeridae was introduced (as Passernia) by the French <link target="polymath">polymath</link> <link target="Constantine Samuel Rafinesque">Constantine Samuel Rafinesque</link> in 1815. Under the classification used in the <link target="Handbook of the Birds of the World">Handbook of the Birds of the World</link> (HBW) main groupings of the sparrows are the true sparrows (genus <link target="Passer">Passer</link>), the <link target="snowfinch">snowfinch</link>es (typically one genus, Montifringilla), and the rock sparrows (<link target="Petronia">Petronia</link> and the <link target="pale rockfinch">pale rockfinch</link>). These groups are similar to each other, and are each fairly homogeneous, especially Passer. Some classifications also include the sparrow-weavers (<link target="Plocepasser">Plocepasser</link>) and several other African genera (otherwise classified among the <link target="weaver (bird)">weavers</link>, Ploceidae) which are morphologically similar to Passer. According to a study of molecular and skeletal evidence by <link target="Jon Fjeldså">Jon Fjeldså</link> and colleagues, the <link target="cinnamon ibon">cinnamon ibon</link> of the Philippines, previously considered to be a <link target="white-eye">white-eye</link>, is a sister taxon to the sparrows as defined by the HBW. They therefore classify it as its own subfamily within Passeridae.<h>Behaviour and ecology</h></p>
<p>Sparrows are generally social birds, with many species breeding in loose colonies and most species occurring in flocks during the non-breeding season. The <link target="great sparrow">great sparrow</link> is an exception, breeding in solitary pairs and remaining only in small family groups in the non-breeding season. Most sparrows form large roosting aggregations in the non-breeding seasons that contain only a single species (in contrast to multi-species flocks that might gather for foraging). Sites are chosen for cover and include trees, thick bushes and reed beds. The assemblages can be quite large with up to 10,000 house sparrows counted in one roost in Egypt.</p>
<p>
The sparrows are some of the few passerine birds that engage in <link target="dust bath">dust bath</link>ing. Sparrows will first scratch a hole in the ground with their feet, then lie in it and fling dirt or sand over their bodies with flicks of their wings. They will also bathe in water, or in dry or melting snow. Water bathing is similar to dust bathing, with the sparrow standing in shallow water and flicking water over its back with its wings, also ducking its head under the water. Both activities are social, with up to a hundred birds participating at once, and is followed by preening and sometimes group singing.<h>Relationships with humans</h></p>
<p>
Sparrows may be the most familiar of all wild birds worldwide. Many sparrow species commonly live in agricultural areas, and for several, human settlements are a primary habitat. The Eurasian tree and house sparrows are particularly specialised in living around humans and inhabit cities in large numbers. 17 of the 26 species recognised by the Handbook of the Birds of the World are known to nest on and feed around buildings.</p>
<p>Grain-eating species, in particular the house and Sudan golden sparrows, can be significant agricultural pests. Sparrows can be beneficial to humans as well, especially by eating insect pests. Attempts at the large-scale control of sparrows have failed to affect sparrow populations significantly, or have been accompanied by major increases in insect attacks probably resulting from a reduction of sparrows, as in the <link target="Four Pests Campaign">Great Sparrow Campaign</link> in 1950s China.</p>
<p>Because of their familiarity, the house sparrow and other sparrows are frequently used to represent the common and vulgar, or the lewd. Birds usually described later as sparrows are referred to in many works of ancient literature and religious texts in Europe and western Asia. These references may not always refer specifically to sparrows, or even to small, seed-eating birds, but later writers who were inspired by these texts often had the house sparrow and other members of the family in mind. In particular, sparrows were associated by the ancient Greeks with <link target="Aphrodite">Aphrodite</link>, the goddess of love, due to their perceived lustfulness, an association echoed by later writers such as <link target="Chaucer">Chaucer</link> and <link target="Shakespeare">Shakespeare</link>.</p>
<p>Jesus&apos;s use of &quot;sparrows&quot; as an example of divine providence in the <link target="Gospel of Matthew">Gospel of Matthew</link> also inspired later references, such as that in Shakespeare&apos;s <link target="Hamlet">Hamlet</link> and the <link target="Gospel music">Gospel</link> <link target="hymn">hymn</link> <link target="His Eye Is on the Sparrow">His Eye Is on the Sparrow</link>.</p>
<p>Sparrows are represented in ancient Egyptian art very rarely, but an <link target="Egyptian hieroglyph">Egyptian hieroglyph</link> G37 is based on the house sparrow. The symbol had no phonetic value and was used as a determinative in words to indicate small, narrow, or bad.</p>
<p>Sparrows have been kept as pets at many times in history, even though most are not particularly colourful and their songs are unremarkable. They are also difficult to keep, as pet sparrows must be raised by hand and a considerable amount of insects are required to feed them. Nevertheless, many are successful in hand raising orphaned or abandoned baby sparrows.</p>
<p>The earliest mentions of pet sparrows are from the Romans. Not all the passeri mentioned, often as pets, in Roman literature were necessarily sparrows, but some accounts of them clearly describe their appearance and habits.<h>References</h></p>
<p>
Works cited
</p>
</content>
</article>
</wikipedia>
